Guide to the Cornwall Writers Collection 1792-1990 (Bulk 1792-1970) MS 036 MS 036 MS 036
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Writers Collection
1792-1990
, (Bulk 1792-1970)
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 036
1 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection consists of documents related to writers associated with Cornwall.
Provenance
This collection was begun by local historian E.C. Starr, as part of his interest in prominent people with ties to Cornwall, and expanded by Michael Gannett, a former president of the Cornwall Historical Society and himself the son of a Cornwall writer.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
"This collection includes works by poets, journalists, editors and authors, and relates to individuals who were both natives of Cornwall, as well as part-time residents of the community. Several writers in this collection were either Cornwall natives, or descended from Cornwall families. Mabel Potter Daggett (1871-1927) was descended from the Cornwall Daggett family and wrote on religious subjects. George Llewelyn Miner (1823-1893) was a lifelong resident of Cornwall who both taught school and wrote. His kinsman, Leigh R. Miner (1864-1935), was also an educator. He taught at the Hampton Institute, which he also wrote about and photographed. Celia E. Gardner (1846-unknown) was a novelist originally from Cornwall who moved to New Jersey. Cornwall historian E.C. Starr was interested in the works of poet Grace Stone Field Page (1890-1962) because of her possible relation to the Stone family of Cornwall, although the link was never verified. Most of the individuals in this collection moved to Cornwall from New York City. Joseph Blumenthal (1897-1990) was a New Yorker who moved to Cornwall, where he passed away in July 1990. Blumenthal was a printer and publisher who founded the Spiral Press. Lewis Gannett (1891-1966) also moved to Cornwall from New York, where he wrote for the New York Herald-Tribune. Gannett and his wife, artist Ruth Chrisman Gannett (1896-1979) settled on Cream Hill where they continued to work at writing and illustrating. Another New York native who moved to Cornwall was Montgomery Hare (1911-1998), a playwright and poet. According to E.C. Starr, author Dorothy Scarborough (1878-1935), who taught literature at Columbia University, owned a home on West Cornwall Road. Chard Powers Smith (1894-1977), an author and poet, also came to Cornwall from New York and settled in Cornwall Hollow. Brothers Carl Van Doren (1885-1950) and Mark Van Doren (1894-1972) were perhaps the best known writers to come to Cornwall from New York City, where they both at one time taught at Columbia University.Other writers found in this collection had less permanent ties to the community. Courtlandt Canby (1914-2004) and his father Henry Seidel Canby (1878-1961) were both writers and summer residents of Cornwall. The elder Canby was best known for his literature reviews, and his son wrote for periodicals, such as The Atlantic. Magazine writer June Mellie Robbins (1925-1993) was a resident of Sharon, but was married in Cornwall in 1972.There are also several individuals in this section whose connections to Cornwall are unknown. These are historian Bessie Blake, poet Lucine Finch, writer Meta Lander, Vassar President Henry Noble MacCracken, politician and historian Townsend Scudder, and magazine writer Ray Thompson. "
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains mostly copies of works by each writer and reviews of their work. With the exception of the Van Doren Christmas cards and two pieces by Lew Gannett there is no unpublished materials in this collection.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by writer then chronologically.
The files are grouped into 24 series:
Lucien Hugh Alexander
Anonymous
Bessie Blake
Joseph Blumenthal
Courtland Canby
Henry Seidel Canby
Mabel Potter Daggett
Lucine Finch
Lewis Gannett
Celia E. Gardner
Montgomery Hare
Meta Lander
Henry Noble MacCracken
George Llewellyn Miner
Leigh R. Miner
Adelaide F. Oakley
Grace Stone Field Page
June Mellie Robbins
Dorothy Scarborough
Townsend Scudder
Chard Powers Smith
Ray Thompson
Carl Van Doren
Mark Van Doren
Authors--United States.; Articles; Correspondence; poems; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972; Van Doren, Carl, 1885-1950; Thompson, Ray; Smith, Chard Powers, 1894-1977; Scudder, Townsend; Scarborough, Dorothy, 1878-1935; Robbins, June Melie; Page, Grace Stone Field; Oakley, Adelaide F.; Miner, Leigh Richmond, 1864-1935; Miner, George Llewellyn; MacCracken, H. N. (Henry Noble), 1880-; Lander, Meta, 1813-1901; Hare, Montgomery; Gardner, Celia E. (Celia Emmeline), 1844-; Gannett, Lewis, 1891-1966; Finch, Lucine; Daggett, Mabel Potter, 1871-1927; Canby, Henry Seidel, 1878-1961; Canby, Courtlandt; Blumenthal, Joseph, 1897-1990; Blake, Bessie; Alexander, Lucien Hugh, 1866-1926
- Lucien Hugh Alexander
  - "James Wilson, Patriot, and the Wilson Doctrine", 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bessie Blake
  - "A Short History of Connecticut", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Joseph Blumenthal
  - Holiday booklets sent by Ann and Joseph Blumenthal, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Russell Potter Poems printed by Joseph Blumenthal, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Joseph Blumenthal," by Leonard Baskin, et al., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mabel Potter Daggett
  - "The Heathen Invasion," Hampton Columbian Magazine, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Lucine Finch
  - "Nathan’s Little Old Lady," The American Magazine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Poem, "Children", 1914 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Lewis Gannett
  - Correspondence with unnamed Cornwall town official, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Poems by Cornwall People and Lewis: For Lewis", 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Celia E. Gardner
  - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Synopsis of "Won Under Protest," undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Montgomery Hare
  - M, Poems Drawings, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - To Beat the Air, Poems and Drawings, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - The Bare Story, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Meta Lander
  - "Marion Graham, or, Higher Than Happiness", undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Traps For Your Boys", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- George Llewellyn Miner
  - Copy of poem, "What Pedagogue Said to his Brother," originally published in Godey’s Lady’s Book and Magazine, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Copy of poem, "Thought," originally published in Godey’s Lady’s Book and Magazine, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poem, "The Future Home," The Housatonic Ray, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Leigh R. Miner
  - Poem, "A Secret," Our Animal Friends, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Series, "With the Thlingets in Alaska," The Southern Workman and Hampton School Record, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poem, "Sunrise," The Southern Workman, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Poem, "Sunset," The Southern Workman, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Article, "Art Teaching st Hampton," The Southern Workman, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Poem, "Thanksgiving," The Southern Workman, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Poem, "En’ ob Day," The Southern Workman, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Poem, "Sunset," The Southern Workman, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Booklet, "Home Decoration", 1917 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Poem, "Tek Keer Ur Jim," The Outlook, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Adelaide F. Oakley
  - Poem, "Easter Dawn," Enquirer, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Grace Stone Field Page
  - Poem, "Harriet Beecher Stowe," and hymn from dedication of Stowe memorial, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - D.A.R. secretary reports, 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Notice for recitations by Grace S.F. Page, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Notices for book, Verses Serious and Saucy, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
  - Verses Serious and Saucy, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Advertisement for Red Cross recital, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr regarding Grace S. F. Page, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- June Mellie Robbins
  - Newspaper image, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Dorothy Scarborough
  - "What the Poets Have Said of Christmas," International Book Review, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Chard Powers Smith
  - Review, "Chard Powers Smith’s New Novel," The New York Times Book Review, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Poem, "Sonnet", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Review of Turn of the Dial, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Ray Thompson
  - Poem, "Recipe For Sleep", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Carl Van Doren
  - Article, "Matthew Bradford", 1924 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Review of Jane Mecom: The Favorite Sister of Benjamin Franklin, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - The Literacy Guild of America, with image of editor Carl Van Doren, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Mark Van Doren
  - Article, "The Real Tragedy of the Farmer," Harper’s Magazine, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Bound collection of articles and images, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Christmas cards from Dorothy and Mark Van Doren, 1947-1971 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Yelping Hill
  - Henry Noble MacCracken
    - "A Social Philosopher," The Saturday Review of Literature, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Henry Seidel Canby
    - Literature reviews, 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    - Photo, in "The Book of the Month Club" pamphlet, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Lewis Gannett, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "The Age of Canby," Newsweek, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Courtlandt Canby
    - "A Letter From Persepolis," The Atlantic, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Townsend Scudder
    - "Townsend Scudder Dusts Off History", 1947 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Singing at Yelping Hill, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - The Amazing Women of Yelping Hill Program sheet, ca. 2012 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    General
    Persons presented about include: Helen Trowbridge, Mary McClelland, Tilla Havesi, Barbara Ensor, Dorothy Lee, Ruth Adams, and M.I. Cake.
    Presentors include: Ann Trowbridge, Deb Cake, Jill Cutler, Joy Wyatt, Anne Schwartz, Sabra Lee, Heidi Cunnick, and Louise Beach.
- Miscellanea
  - "Wisdom, a Poem", 1792 (Box 1, Folder 2)